A data set by itself is not capable of explaining
the full reality behind the data set. A data set
about an event is only a part of what happens
in reality and a lot of information and context
goes missing. There are many ways to create
visualizations and one of them is collaboration
between domain experts and visualization
designers. But the issue here is that domain
experts are very knowledgeable about their
topic but oftentimes do not have the knowledge
about visualization design. On the other hand,
visualization designers are very skilled in making
visualizations but do not have enough knowledge
about the context behind the data. This lack of
understanding causes miscommunication between
designers and domain experts. This evidence
can also be found in literature. The comments
such as "designers inferences about data were
often inaccurate" and "anticipating all of the
implications of scale and interaction for given
data sets remains challenging" indicate that it is
easy to be misled and if this could be addressed
then it would help the visualization design
process. To that end, we develop a system called
the data therapist. Data therapist aims to enhance
the understanding of datasets for lay audience by
eliciting knowledge through annotations about the
data from experts. We let experts make annotations
to the data that's data set through a mixture of
interaction approach to question answering and
user-driven annotation for extracting knowledge
from domain experts. Data therapist has three
ways to make annotations. First is annotating the
overall data set. Second is annotating a specific
region of interest. And third is answering
data therapist initiated questions about the
dataset. Here's the first method where the user
can make annotations about the overall data set.
The second method is where users can set
specific data instance and then add annotations.
You can also conduct simple analysis by referring
to visualizations such as histogram and scatter
plots to identify the correlation and anomalies
and choose items of the expert's interest.
The third method is where questions are provided
and the user can add annotations by answering the
provided questions. These questions are composed
of LLM generated questions where you see a grid
symbol and a set of predefined questions that
aim to enrich the descriptions about the data
set. Once the answers are added, then the system
verifies if the answer aligns with the question.
Finally, as an output, we provide a CSV
file that show the list of all annotation
and set of questions and answers that the
user has annotated. These annotations then
could be used to create reports that help
the understanding of topics for the lay
audience or visualization designers. Here we
present an example of how our system is used.
For an in-depth analysis of these annotations,
please refer to our paper. Our main
focus is in understanding how their
the data therapists created annotations help
bridge the knowledge gap between experts and
lay audience by comparing annotations
with those from human guidance. Thank you.